Hi, welcome back to Nagarjuna,
Arya Nagarjuna, and we
stopped at this point here.
We were talking about how do
causes create their results.
We reached a part called
RGYUS 'BRAS BU SKYE BA'I
BYA BA SBYOR BA BYED PA
How is it exactly that a
cause triggers a result.
And then we're going to
discuss whether or not a cause
can exist in and of itself.
This is all part of an
idea of a discussion
about the possibility that
causes and their results
are not one and the same thing,
that they are separate things.
Which would we normally say?
Is the cause the result
or are the cause and result separate?
What would we normally say?
Yeah. Separate.
If the cause was the result, then
I wouldn't have to be here today
because I already prepared the class.
That would be the class.
So now we're going to
discuss the possibility
that the cause and the
result are discreet entities,
or separate from one another.
Can they be separate things?
And that's a little trickier
because that's what we normally think.
And there are places in this book
where Choney Lama, in my opinion,
is scrambling to make an outline.
He's trying to make logical sense
out of Nagarjuna's poetry,
especially the whole flow.
So he has sort of
a very interesting move
here, like a basketball move.
He says the way I see it
you can impose an outline on this section
called 'The Seven Reasons
Why Cause and Their Results
cannot be Separate'.
Seven Reasons Why Causes and Their Results
Cannot be Separate.
So he's going to go
through seven sections now
and he's going to point out
seven problems with the idea
that causes and their
results are separate.
And personally, I can remember
when I reached this section.
It felt like he was repeating himself.
It felt like ideas were coming up
that had already been treated before.
And I checked and I checked and
what I believe is what
we had discussed before
was mainly in the context of the convening
of the causes and conditions.
When the causes and
conditions come together,
what is their relationship to the result?
And now he's taking the causes out of
the convening of the causes and conditions
and he's saying, what's
the specific relationship
between the cause in
isolation and its result?
The cause independent of the convening
of the causes and conditions.
But you're going to
hear the same arguments
and then you're going to get confused
because you're going to think
we covered them already.
Seven different possibilities here.
There's a major mistake
in the Tibetan carving
which took a while to figure out,
and we'll discuss it.
Here's the seven. I'll say them quickly,
And we'll talk about it.
Possibility number one:
the result is triggered
by a cause which has already stopped,
but it is somehow still present.
Number two: the result is triggered,
and in Tibetan and in Sanskrit they say
"in sight of the cause,"
meaning the cause can somehow look ahead
and see a result coming.
I like to call it anticipation,
He calls it in sight,
in sight of the cause.
The result is in sight of the cause,
meaning the cause is like this
and he can see the cause.
He can see the result coming.
That's another possibility.
And in that case would the cause
and the result be separate?
Like that, in a discussion.
Third possibility that
the result is triggered:
we're going to discuss whether
the result is triggered
by contact with the cause or not.
Can there be contact
between cause and result?
And that's a difficult question. Because?
By the time the result
comes out the contact is...
the cause is gone.
So how can they ever make contact?
If they don't make contact,
why couldn't that same cause cause a pizza
that you're going to buy me tonight?
As just an example.
Number four is
the cause void of the result
in the time of the cause or not?
Is the result somehow present
in the time of the cause
within the cause, as
potential, for example.
Fifth possibility,
and this is where the
Tibetan carving went off.
Does the fact of the
result being triggered
have an inherent cause and
result contained within it?
That's where the Tibetan goes off.
It's difficult. We'll talk about it.
Possibility number six: is the
result triggered by a cause,
when the result is triggered by a cause
is the cause the same as the result
or separate from the result?
We already said they were separate
but he's going to go there.
Number seven: is the result
which is triggered by a cause,
does it have its own nature or not?
What's the status of the result?
So let's go through them one by one
and you'll see.
To say all seven of those
in a row is too much.
Sorry.
Here's possibility number one.
To repeat, option number one of the seven,
or mini examination, mini investigation,
was: is it possible that a result
is triggered by a cause
that has to stop first
and then the result comes?
Got it?
That's how we normally think of things.
Like the seed stops and the tree starts,
something like that.
So he's going to examine is it possible
that the result is triggered by a cause
where that cause has already
stopped, technically,
because it became the result.
That's another question.
And here, if you're reading the Tibetan,
Nagarjuna uses the word NUB PA
for 'stopped', for the cause.
And NUB PA means
for the sun to go down,
or for the Dharma to
disappear in the world.
These are the verb, this is the verb.
And he's used that verb for the cause.
Does the cause disappear
behind the horizon
before the result comes out?
That's the way he wants to say it.
,'BRAS BU SKYES PA JI LTAR SKYED,
How could that be?
,'BRAS BU DANG NI 'BREL BA'I RGYU,
So how could the cause stop
and then produce the result?
Because there wouldn't be any relationship
between cause and effect
because it's a principle of Buddhist logic
that for two things to have a relationship
they both have to be existing.
Duh!
What are the two possible
kinds of relationships?
That's another story.
Well I'll tell you.
No, that's another story, long story.
Anyway, for two things
to have a relationship
they both have to be
in the room, basically.
And if one of them has already disappeared
then there's no discussion
of a relationship.
,'BRAS BU DANG NI 'BREL BA'I RGYU,
,GNAS PAS KYANG NI JI LTAR SKYED,
But if you're saying that the
cause is somehow still around
by the time the result comes out,
then there's a problem there also.
Then there would be a piece of the result
that was existing in the time of the cause
before the result had occurred.
If they ever, if they touch
anywhere, there's a problem.
If the cause happened in 2011
and the result happened in 2012,
and somehow they touch each other
then, what was it, midnight
on the 31st of December
and they shared a 10 minutes?
They stretched somehow?
And if they never make contact
then anything could cause anything
because there's no necessary contact
between the cause and the result.
Then any result could
come out of any cause.
,CI STE RGYU 'BRAS MA 'BREL NA,
,'BRAS BU GANG ZHIG SKYED PAR BYED,
And that's the whole argument.
So you see a picture here of
a rabbit coming out of a hat.
I was trying to find something
where you had a result without a cause,
with no visible cause around.
So that's kind of the feeling here.
We don't know where the rabbit came from.
The rabbit wasn't in the
hat the moment before.
There was no rabbit of the moment before.
Somehow he just popped out.
It's almost an effect without a cause.
A result without a cause.
That's what the picture
is supposed to indicate.
So this first option is
that the cause has stopped
and then the result comes.
And that's kind of how
we feel instinctively
about how cause and effect works.
I agree the cause and effect
can't exist at the same time.
That gets messy. But
how about if the cause
just goes up to a certain place and stops
and then the result
starts. Can't we say that?
And he says, well, then you've
got a result without a cause,
which is not possible,
which is like a rabbit
coming out of a hat.
I got very uncomfortable at this point
and I had a deep realization,
which I've been thinking
about for a couple of days.
Nowhere in this book does
he tell you an option.
Nowhere in this... he only,
it's like only complaining about your wife
and never making a positive suggestion.
You know what I mean?
The whole book is saying
what things are not.
Even the opening verse is
SKYE BA MED PA, CHAD MED PA (SIC)
Like this
MED PA MED PA MED PA MED
With no
YOD PA
He doesn't describe the option to nothing
which is dependent origination.
He never goes there.
Nobody in this book goes
to a real explanation
of mental seeds and projections
and things created by...
There's no explanation in
this root text or commentary,
specific explanation of
how we create things,
like the pen explanation.
It's missing here.
And it gets scary here.
It gets uncomfortable for the audience
because now he's saying it's not possible
that the cause could stop and
then a result come out of it.
And it's also not possible that the cause
could not stop and the result come out.
And then, and he keeps saying by nature.
These things cannot happen by nature.
These things don't happen
from their own side.
These things don't
happen self-existentingly
but he never tells you what's the option.
He never tells you what it would be like
for something to start
through mental seeds
or through dependence. He never tells you.
He just tells you
throughout what they're not.
The whole book is a not book.
It's like a bad day with
your partner or something.
They just keep telling
you, they don't say:
"I like this"... They're
just: "I don't like this,
I don't like this."
And you get to the end of the book
and he didn't say he liked anything.
And so I thought here let's
look at the ice cream,
which is very important to me.
And this is a very
extremely important picture
for the rest of your life.
So this is how causes
really are creating effects.
This is how it really happens.
Because nobody in the
whole book tells you.
He just keeps saying what's not true.
And he wants us to struggle.
He wants us to think:
Well, what's really going on?
And he never tells us.
He just keeps saying it's
not this. It's not this.
It's not this. And you'll see
he just keeps saying that.
There's no chapter called
the chocolate sauce.
So here we go. The white ice cream
represents the parts of a thing,
like the parts of a car,
or the parts of a pen. You guys got a pen?
I've got a pen.
Pens and tight jeans don't go together.
I can get it out. I just want to prove it.
So,
the pen of yesterday
didn't cause the pen of today,
or the factory, the pen factory,
which is the cause, didn't make this pen.
This pen was not a result of a pen factory
in Japan or something like that.
Well so what's really going on?
Well either the factory closed
and the pen came out.
The cause stopped and
then the pen came out.
They stopped that day's production
and then tomorrow the pen came out.
Or the pen came out at the end of the day
and then they all went home.
And the factory... that's it.
The factory that made this
pen is no longer there.
Maybe tomorrow's factory is there.
And then the other possibility is that
the exact factory that made this pen
is still doing the same
thing it made this pen with
on this pen, while the
pen's already there.
The factory's still making this pen
after Geshe-la's writing with this pen.
That's the other possibility.
So what's really happening?
So yesterday we went out for
TSE BCU. We had ice cream.
There was gelato, two kinds of gelato:
strawberry and vanilla.
And then they think of those
as the parts of the pen.
So here's the strawberry.
There's the ball of strawberry gelato.
Here's the ball of...
Here's the ball of vanilla gelato.
And then you put them both in a bowl
and then you pour
chocolate sauce over them.
And that's kind of how we create things.
There's a bottom half of the pen.
There's the upper half of the pen.
They are there. They are
there when we enter the room.
And then our mind
perceives these two pieces
and then a seed opens in my mind
and a picture comes out.
I like to call it a luminous picture
because it... On the day that you see
pictures coming out of your mind,
they will look like neon pictures, neon.
They are bright. They are luminous.
They are artificially bright.
The picture of a pen
doesn't look like this.
When a mental seed opens for pen,
what comes out of your mind is
an impossibly well-defined,
neon picture of a pen.
And then that flies, there's
even a physical sensation
of that seed, that image, luminous image,
flying out of your mind,
somewhere in your forehead,
which is weird, but that's the way it is,
and it lands on the objects.
It lands on the pieces
and it unifies them.
And then the dog has a different picture
coming out of their karmic seeds.
And that's a picture of a chew toy
and it lands on the same
two balls of ice cream
and coats them, and then it
becomes a, what do you call it?
Fudge.
Fudge sundae or something.
So and it is a kind of coat.
That's why I chose this picture.
I used to use a different picture
that had kind of skinny
streams of chocolate
and I wasn't satisfied with it.
When you really see it happen,
it'll be almost a complete
coating, but not quite.
So it will look like chocolate
sauce poured on ice cream.
When you finally see it yourself,
which is within a few hours
of seeing emptiness directly,
you'll see your mind
making these pictures.
So that's what's really happening.
There's a cause, which is a seed.
There's a result, which is a tree.
And the relationship between them
is an artificial creation
of your mental seeds.
And that cause and effect relationship
is the chocolate sauce. And
the two balls of ice cream
are the seed and the tree.
What bothers Nagarjuna
is that without the chocolate sauce,
there is no, there
cannot be a relationship
because if they touch
somewhere then that part
is ice cre... vanilla and strawberry --
and that's not possible.
So either they touch or they don't touch.
If they do touch, it's
a third thing going on.
If they don't touch, then how
can they be cause and effect?
Because they never meet each other.
Then the answer, the punchline
is that your mental seeds
are throwing out like a parachute shape
and that covers the
two balls of ice cream,
the cause and effect,
and your mind creates
the cause and effect relationship;
an illusion of a cause
and effect relationship.
So that's what's really
going on and they never,
I don't believe they're ever
going to say it in the book.
So I thought it would
be nice to say it here
because it's frustrating.
The punchline is almost always the same:
the cause cannot touch the result
because then there would
be a point of contact
where the result existed in the past.
And they can't not touch because then
that particular seed could cause a pizza
or inflation, or
just weird stuff that's
not connected to it.
But they can't be connected
because then they have to
exist in the same time.
If they are connected in
any way, "relationship",
then a piece of one has to be in the past
or a piece of the other
has to be in the future
and that's not possible either.
So it gets frustrating, nobody tells you,
and then he just goes on.
It gets frustrating. So yeah,
the answer is: your mind
is creating the connection
between cause and effect.
Your mind is seeing a connection
where someone else's mind
might not see a connection.
And for them the connection
might be different.
And that's a cool thing.
The punchline, but the super
punchline is that that's proof
that you have to be nice to other people.
And by the way if someone explains to you
the emptiness of cause and effect
and doesn't talk about
being nice to other people,
I don't believe they understand it.
If they're not talking about morality
within three minutes,
then they don't really understand.
Because the natural question
of any human being would be
"I like two balls of ice cream
and chocolate sauce, Geshe-la.
How do I get it?"
How do I make it happen?
And if the cause and effect
ice cream sauce theory is correct,
and you understand it,
the next question you should be asking me
is how do I make the right sauce to get
a million dollars?
And stop working so hard. Right, Osiris?
How can I just take care of that?
And if you don't ask that question,
then I'm suspicious that you
don't understand the point,
which is if my karmic seeds
are creating the sauce
that combines cause and effect,
how can I create more sauce for money
or for love or for good
health or for mental peace,
all the other good stuff, a better world?
So I'm going to come back
to the chocolate sauce
from time to time during
the next few classes,
just to remind you how
it's really happening.
Because when we discuss seven bad options
for how cause and effect really happens,
we have to remember to
forget the chocolate sauce.
We have to remember to
We can't talk about karma.
We can't talk about things coming from me.
When we say self-existent,
we're talking about
independent of my luminous image. Got it?
And you've got to remember that.
When all these seven options
are all self-existent,
RANG BZHIN GYIS YOD PA
he keeps saying that
over and over again.
And you start to not see it anymore
because he keeps repeating it,
but you've got to say that.
You've got to say that.
These are seven bad options
because they all involve cause and effect
which is coming from its own side,
which is coming this way.
All right, so don't forget
the chocolate sauce.
I don't.
I'm going to throw in
some Sanskrit words here
that I think are helpful.
I'm trying to limit these words.
I'm trying to stick to
about 20 words or something,
because I don't want to overwhelm you
and I also don't want to give you a word
that you're never going to use
or that you're never going to see.
I want to give you the
really important ones
that are kind of like tools
that you have to have.
So one word that I'd
like to talk about now
is called 'samgati'.
The Tibetan is
LHAN CIG PHRAD PA
LHAN CIG PHRAD PA means
PHRAD PA means to make contact.
LHAN CIG means same place and same time.
So that, I call it the crucial moment
when cause and result
supposedly make contact,
like the seed and the tree.
There's a special tiny point of contact,
which a mathematician
would say is a point,
a point with no width,
a theoretical point, point of contact.
So that's called
LHAN CIG PHRAD PA
They touch each other.
Somewhere the seed touches the tree.
And the 'gati' you know from Heart Sutra.
What's that?
"gati gati paragati
parasamgati bodhi svaha".
Yeah, go, go, go.
Go, go, go. Really go. Super go.
So gati, and then that comes into
the word go in English.
So that's easy.
/gam is the full root
and come comes from that
also, if you're interested.
The other word I'd like you to learn
is drstva. And that means seen
or a seeing.
We're going to discuss it, as I mentioned,
in the sense of anticipation
or the potential for a result and a cause,
because if you don't feel comfortable
with results stopping and
then the cause starting,
would you feel more
comfortable with saying
the cause anticipates the result?
Would you feel more comfortable that way?
That somehow the result is
anticipated by the cause.
Does that make you more comfortable?
He's going to discuss that possibility.
He doesn't say the word anticipate,
he says within sight of.
Is the result within sight of the cause?
Is the cause somehow
anticipating the result?
And the result is a little
farther away than touching,
but it's still there.
Not yet, but it's there.
It's kind of like potential.
And I like this root, the
Indo-European is /derk,
it's not dork.
'Derk' means to see in Indo-European
and the word dragon comes from that
because a dragon is, means
the one with the evil eye.
The word dragon means the
one with the evil eye.
It means the one with the eye.
I did my three year retreat
in the Dragoon Mountains,
and I was curious whether that was related
to dragon and it is, somehow.
I don't remember why.
But you can look it up. It
means a special kind of soldier.
A sentry, in a sense, maybe
the one with the eyes.
The last word I'd like to
discuss here in the Sanskrit
is 'śūnya', say śūnya-
Long U, śūnya
which means STONG, which means devoid of,
and it requires the instrumental.
So in English you say,
this fresh tissue is devoid of boogers.
Now it's not devoid of boogers.
Just that devoid means,
I was trying to get some excuse to use it.
So in English you say devoid of.
It means that it's a fresh tissue
and it doesn't have any
other things inside yet.
But in the Asian languages,
Tibetan and Sanskrit,
you have to use the instrumental.
'Devoid by'.
Just remember that, because
it's going to come in handy.
You don't say devoid
of, you say devoid by.
For example,
SNABS BUS @DRING@ MED STONG BA
means devoid by boogers.
And not devoid of boogers.
I knew you wanted to know that.
But the problem is here,
he's going to use 'STONG'
in two different senses.
I looked up the word today
because I couldn't remember it.
Equivocate.
He's going to use the word
empty in two different meanings,
and he kind of cheats.
He says, and we'll see why,
one thing he says "cause
can't be empty of the result
"because an empty result
would be like empty,
"would be like NAM MKHA'I ME TOG,"
a flower sprouting in mid air,
with no roots, no water, no
soil, nothing, just boop.
He uses it in a sense
of the void as a space,
and then he's going to switch
between two kinds of void.
So just be aware.
When you say STONG PA,
or STONG PA NYID,
you mean the void, or
emptiness of self-existence.
But when you just say STONG, 'śūnya' here,
śūnya, not 'śūnyatā', not emptiness,
but just empty, then it's not clear
what you're talking about.
Could be empty mind. It
could be an empty cup.
Could be empty of self-existence.
We don't know yet.
I'm just saying be aware,
śūnya, by itself, is ambiguous.
It needs some, you need someone
to tell you which śūnya.
It has a long U, which
often changes to AU.
All Sanskrit vowels have
three degrees of strength:
short U, long U, and then AU.
And then AU becomes OW.
And the AU often changes to AV.
AU as a combination in ancient
Sanskrit, Greek, Latin,
often changes to AV, so you get,
shu becomes cave, as a cavity.
Because the U changed,
the AU changed to AV.
And the C changed, became
a hard K from a soft S,
and it became cave, or cavity.
Vault comes from that.
Swell comes from that
and hole comes from that,
because H's come from K and like that.
Excavate, cumulous clouds,
church comes from that
because a churches were
originally perceived as
mighty things with might inside.
Empty inside, like the power
to just grow, grow, grow.
Churches were seen as places
of hot air expanding.
Something like that.
No, power expanding, not hot air.
Those words are going to come in handy.
I'll say them again.
'Samgati', which means is there
ever a meeting of the two.
'Drstva', which means can we see
or anticipate a result coming,
even in the time of the cause.
And then 'śūnya',
when we say the cause
or the result is empty,
what do we mean?
Here we go.
Remember that we're going through
seven combinations of possibilities,
and here is the second one.
The result is triggered, and
a lot of the possibilities
are questions: is it this or is it this?
Possibility number two is:
is the result triggered within
sight of the cause or not?
Is the result triggered
in sight of the cause,
in view of the cause,
which kind of means presence of the cause?
Is the cause still standing around
by the time the result came out?
And is the cause able to see the result?
Can the result, in a sense,
be anticipated by the cause?
And here's his arguments.
,RGYUS NI MTHONG DANG MA MTHONG BAR,
,'BRAS BU SKYED PAR MI BYED DO,,
He says both wrong.
Neither is the result seen by the cause,
nor is it not seen by the cause.
RGYUS NI RANG GI 'BRAS BU
MTHONG NAS SAM MA MTHONG BAR
It's not that the cause
can anticipate the result,
because
MTHONG NAS GRUB ZIN PAS
when you talk about seeing something,
the thing you see should have
come into existence already.
When you talk about seeing something.
If you see something, it should have come
into existence already.
Even as a potential, it should
have come into existence
as a potential result.
And there wouldn't be any purpose
to the thing happening again.
If a thing could be anticipated,
if you could see a result in the future
that's likely or probable,
then in a way you've already
made contact with that result,
and there wouldn't be any reason
for it to grow again.
For there to be another
result happen, just that one.
If the result didn't happen,
there's no way you could
anticipate, you couldn't see it.
If it didn't have any
existential status, then
you couldn't see it.
If you could see it, then
it had existential status
and there's no reason for it
to happen again a second time.
Now, if you said I saw a potential
result, that's different.
But if you say I saw
the result, how's that?
Inside out.
And he says if the result is that solid,
upcoming result is that
solid, then there's no reason
for the cause to work
so hard to create it.
And then he says the job,
the cause would have to apply
for unemployment benefits, next picture.
Like it wouldn't have, it's
job would be done already
and it would have to, it would get fired
because the job was already filled.
RGYUS 'BRAS BU MA MTHONG BAR
RANG BZHIN GYIS SKYED PAR MI BYED DE,
But if you say the cause
cannot anticipate the result
and cannot see the result coming,
SKYED NA RGYU GCIG GIS KYANG
'BRAS BU THAMS CAD CIG CAR SKYED
If it's not necessary to be able
to see a potential result
in the time of the cause,
and if it's not possible,
then it makes sense that
all possible results
would be possible from a single cause.
Because there's no reason why
one would be more likely than another.
If one result were not
more likely than another,
then it would make sense
that a single cause
could trigger any result.
If there's no more likelihood
of a similar result
than a non-similar result.
Because you can't anticipate
it because you can't see it,
because it doesn't have
any existential status in the present yet.
We got a picture for that
and I forget what the picture was.
Oh yeah, he says all possible results
would be triggered by a single cause
if a cause couldn't, if
you could not anticipate
a particular result
from a particular cause,
then all possible results would
result from a single cause.
If there was no more likelihood
that one result would
happen than another result,
then one cause would create,
one wheat seed would create
a whole field of wheat.
Because there's no more likelihood
that it would create one stalk of wheat
than any other stalk of wheat.
There wouldn't be any more likelihood.
Odds would be canceled.
If there was no amount of the result
present in the time of the cause,
then the probability of all
things happening is 100%.
And the probability of
one thing happening is 0%.
Because you can't anticipate it,
because it doesn't have
any kind of existence yet,
not even as a potential.
Because there's no relationship.
They're totally separate.
They don't share any kind,
they're not holding hands anywhere.
Are you all right?
By the way,
here's a tiny RANG LUGS.
Tim, what's a RANG LUGS?
Sorry, I have allergies, I'm sorry.
Say again?
Yeah, RANG LUGS is, LUGS,
and here's a rare occurrence where he says
"what do we think?"
And I complain that he hadn't bring up,
he didn't bring up ice cream yet.
And he has a lame RANG LUGS here.
RANG LUGS LA NI RGYUS 'BRAS
BU MA MTHONG BAR SKYED KYANG
Our position, if you want to know,
is that the cause does not create a result
which is anticipated,
but still that's not,
that doesn't contradict saying
it couldn't create a
cause in and of itself.
Can you anticipate a result?
No.
Does that mean it has to create a cause?
That the cause has to create
a result in and of itself?
Not either.
It's not contradictory to say
a cause has no self nature,
if it does not anticipate its result.
I'll say it again.
If us, if our side says that
there is no anticipation
of a particular result
by a particular cause,
that doesn't contradict us also saying
that the cause doesn't automatically lead
to a particular result.
And then he doesn't help us. He goes on.
And that's only Choney Lama being nice.
There's nothing in Nagarjuna about it.
Listen to the recording three times.
Option number three of seven,
the result is triggered
by contact with the cause.
Let's examine,
BRTAGS PA ... BRTAGS PA
let's examine whether or not
the result is triggered
through contact with the cause.
Is there contact between
the cause and the result,
or not?
That's what we're going to look at.
And this is long, this is
four verses in the Sanskrit
which is unusually long.
And there's a lot of options here.
We're going to start them, and by the way,
one of the lines of
the Tibetan is missing,
which makes it more interesting.
And I went and recovered
it from the Tengyur,
due to the fact that we have ALL,
which typed in the entire Tengyur,
which recovered the only
Tengyur outside of Tibet.
The only one in India,
that ALL was the first,
ALL brought the first Tengyur out of Tibet
in modern times.
And that was quite an adventure story.
We should tell it some day.
Okay, I'll tell you,
we have a few minutes.
There's a printery called
Derge in east Tibet
and I can talk about the Red Guards.
During the cultural revolution,
the Red Guards came to burn that library.
And there was a monk who was
trying to protect the library
and it's like an army
facing a single monk.
And he had this inspiration.
He took all his clothes off,
and he went and got and ax
and he danced around the door
of the library with his ax
and he said anyone who comes in here
will lose their head.
And they called the general of the army.
This is the story I heard.
And he came up, he
said, "What's going on?"
They said, "We want to burn this library,
"but there's this crazy
monk staying there.
"He's got a, he's threatening
to cut off anyone's head
"who comes, and he's got
his penis hanging out
"and it's weird.
What should we do, should we
just shoot him in the head?"
And he said "No, no, leave him,
we'll do it later and
we'll burn it later."
And then they forgot to burn it.
They never got back to it,
and so those blocks
from the 1700s survived.
210 volumes which, times 1,000.
210,000 times two, because you have to do
to front side and the back side,
now you're talking half a million blocks.
Because there's separate
block for the front side
and a separate block for the back side.
Sometimes they don't get it right,
they put the back of page
three on the back of page,
or on the front of page seven.
And the backs don't have page numbers,
but that makes life interesting.
Anyway, half a million blocks survived,
and no copy was printed
for about 30 years
from the blocks from the 1700s.
And then ALL made it happen
through various means. And we
paid a huge amount of money
to unspecified account,
and we waited for two years.
And the books showed up,
210 volumes.
It's priceless. They're priceless.
And then JB's crew proceeded to type in
the 410,000 pages, and they finished.
420,000 pages. They finished.
And that's why we have it.
And that's why I can replace a line
that was left off of this commentary.
Yay JB. Let's give him a hand.
Good story.
Anyway, we're going to
continue in the next class.
Which option are we on you guys?
We're on option number three. Yeah.
We still got a ways to go.
By the way, these options are long,
and we're going to, when you
get impatient with a text,
slow down.
When you get impatient with a text,
and when you're thinking
you wish it would go faster,
that's the time, if you
really want to be a Yogi,
you purposefully slow yourself down
and you digest it with pleasure,
with shamatha, 'śamatha'.
See you guys in the next class.